<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><Search><pages Count="69"><page Index="1"><![CDATA[Approved by the Government of Nepal, Ministry of Education
                          Curriculum Development Centre (CDC), Sanothimi, Bhaktapur, Nepal.








                  New
                            SOCIAL STUDIES



                                              AND



             POPULATION EDUCATION





                                     Revised and Updated






                                                           8




                                    GRADE









                                               Authors
                                       Matrika Pd. Lamsal

                                           Ganesh Dhakal]]></page><page Index="2"><![CDATA[Published by







                 TU Road, Kuleshwor, Kathmandu, Nepal.
                 Phone: 4672071, 5187211, 5187226 Fax: 00977-1-4672073
                 E-mail: readmorenepal6@gmail.com
                 www.readmorenp.com

                 © Copyright: Publisher 2075 BS

                 First Edition                : 2072 BS
                 Revised Edition              : 2073 BS
                 Revised and Updated Edition  : 2074, 2075, 2076, 2077 BS
                 Revised and Updated Edition : 2078 BS







                     No part of this book may be reproduced or transmitted by any means, electronic,
                  photocopying, recording, or otherwise, without prior written permission of the publisher.
                          Any breach of this condition will entail legal action and prosecution.



                            Language Editor                    Thanks to:
                              Kiran Thapa                  Ishwar Mani Lamsal
                          Grishma Rajbhandari              Krishna Pd. Parajuli
                                                               Sanjeev Rai
                                                        Ramesh Chandra Adhikari

                                                  Layout
                                            Readmore Desktop


                   Printed in Nepal



                  You can exchange this book from your nearest book shop if any binding errors are found.


                                     Read to help others read !
                       We are pleased to inform that a certain amount from each book is allocated to the
                             Charity Fund. The fund is provided to deserving and needy students all over Nepal.
                    The charity always welcomes co-operation and support from all well wishers and agencies.]]></page><page Index="3"><![CDATA[About the book





                       ’s Social Studies and Population Education is a graded series of
            text books intended for the school children of Nepal, and has been specially prepared
            for the English Medium Schools of Nepal. This series has been prepared in accordance
            to the curriculum  prescribed by the CDC, Government of Nepal. This  series gives
            students the basic knowledge about the different branches of the study of Social
            studies e.g. Sociology, Geography, History, Population, Economics etc.
            Salient features of the book:
            Objectives: The book starts with the objectives of the lesson giving the teacher as
            well as the students an idea about what they will be learning by the end of each unit.
            Note to teacher: The lesson also includes note to the teacher to help the teacher
            make the classes more interesting and informative. It gives an idea to the teacher as
            to what resources can be used and what other alternative methods also can be used
            to make the classes fun and interactive.
            Key Term: The language used in the lesson is simple to read and understand. A set of
            keywords have been included which provides the students with the meanings of the
            difficult words that they might come across in the lesson.
            Activities: There are a set of activities after each lesson. It instructs the students to
            gather information practically and makes the lessons relevant in their day to day life.
            These activities help the students to learn the lesson practically as well.

            Exercise: The exercises after each lesson cover the important aspect of the lesson so
            that the students are aware of the areas where they have to concentrate.
            Community work: It has been included for the students to get more exposure and
            an  opportunity  for them to  interact with  their community  and  be aware of  their
            surroundings.
            Review  Exercise:  After  each  unit  there  is  a  section  of  review  exercise  where  the
            students can revise what they have learnt in the previous lessons.
            We would like to express our sincere thanks to Readmore Publishers & Distributors
            for publishing this Social Studies Series. We are thankful to the editors and experts
            whose support and guidance has played an important role in the writing of this book.
            We would  also like to extend our thanks to the schools  and  principals  who  have
            recommended               Social Studies and Population Education book
            to their students and schools.


            We have written this book with utmost care and up to date data but we would like
            to apologize  in case  any  errors are  found.  We  highly  appreciate  the  opinion  and
            constructive suggestions from the teachers and intellectuals.
                                                                                    - Authors]]></page><page Index="4"><![CDATA[Table of Contents




            UNIT 1       WE, OUR COMMUNITY AND NATION
                     1.   Development                                                      7
                     2.   Federal State                                                    11
                     3.   Our Provinces                                                    15
                     4.   Drinking Water                                                   31
                     5.   Energy                                                           36
                     6.   Human Resource                                                   39
                     7.   Development Projects of Nepal                                    43
                          Review Exercise                                                  46

            UNIT 2       OUR SOCIAL NORMS AND VALUES
                     1.   Social Traditions and Customs of Nepal                           48
                     2.   Religions of Nepal                                               52
                     3.   Social Harmony                                                   57
                     4.   Nepal: A Beautiful Garden                                        59
                     5.   National Heritage                                                62
                     6.   International Personality                                        65
                          Review Exercise                                                  69

            UNIT 3       SOCIAL PROBLEMS AND THEIR SOLUTIONS
                     1.   Social Problems                                                  71
                     2.   Corruption                                                       74
                     3.   Drug Abuse                                                       78
                     4.   Conflict and Its Management                                      82
                     5.   Sustainable Development                                          86
                     6.   Good Governance                                                  89
                     7.   International Organizations                                      92
                          Review Exercise                                                  96

            UNIT 4       CIVIC AWARENESS
                     1.   Social Rules                                                     98
                     2.   Human Rights                                                    101
                     3.   Women’s Right                                                   104
                     4.   Inclusiveness                                                   108
                     5.   Provisions of Inclusiveness in Nepal                            111
                     6.   Characteristics of Our Constitution                             114
                     7.   Responsibilities of Citizens                                    117
                     8.   Legislature                                                     120
                     9.   Executive                                                       124
                     10.   Judiciary                                                      128
                          Review Exercise                                                 133

            UNIT 5       OUR EARTH
                     1.   Change of Season                                                135
                     2.   Weather and Climate                                             138
                     3.   Factors Affecting Temperature                                   141
                     4.   Climate Change                                                  145
                     5.   Impacts of Longitude and Latitude                               149
                     6.   Districts and Provinces of Nepal                                152
                     7.   Use of Distance on Maps                                         155
                     8.   Map of Nepal                                                    158
                     9.   Disaster Management                                             160
                     10.   Africa Continent                                               166]]></page><page Index="5"><![CDATA[11.   North America Continent                                        173
                     12.   South America Continent                                        180
                          Review Exercise                                                 187

            UNIT 6       OUR PAST
                     1.   Role of People in The Unification of Nepal                      189
                     2.   Unification of Nepal                                            192
                     3.   The Continuation of Unification and Its End                     195
                     4.   Political Events After Sugauli Treaty                           198
                     5.   Political Activities During The Rana Regime                     201
                     6.   Economic and Social Activities During The Rana Regime           204
                     7.   Major Political Events After 2007 BS and Achievements           207
                     8.   Greek and Roman Civilization                                    210
                     9.   Renaissance                                                     214
                          Review Exercise                                                 217

            UNIT 7       OUR ECONOMIC ACTIVITIES
                     1.   Tourism Industry                                                219
                     2.   Foreign Trade                                                   223
                     3.   Currency                                                        227
                     4.   Bank                                                            230
                     5.   Price Determination of Goods and Price Hiking                   233
                     6.   Capital Formation and Co-operatives                             237
                     7.   The Condition of Employment in Nepal                            240
                          Review Exercise                                                 243

            UNIT 8       OUR INTERNATIONAL RELATION AND CO-OPERATION
                     1.   Our Friendly Nations                                            245
                     2.   United Nations Organization and Its Organs                      248
                     3.   United Nations Organization and Nepal                           253
                     4.   Diplomatic Mission                                              257
                     5.   The Contribution of Nepal in International Sector               260
                          Review Exercise                                                 263

            UNIT 9       AN INTRODUCTION OF POPULATION AND
                         DEMOGRAPHIC STATUS
                     1.   Concept of Demography                                           265
                     2.   Basic Demographic Measurement                                   268
                     3.   Mortality and Migration                                         272
                     4.   Determinants of Population Change                               277
                     5.   Population Composition of Nepal                                 279
                     6.   Population Distribution in Nepal                                281
                     7.   Internal and External Migration in Nepal                        283
                     8.   World’s Population Size and Its Growth                          285
                          Review Exercise                                                 288

            UNIT 10      POPULATION GROWTH AND MANAGEMENT
                     1.   Population and Quality of Life                                  290
                     2.   Measures for Population Management                              293
                     3.   The Problems of Population Management in Nepal                  295
                     4.   Roles of International Organizations in Population Management    298
                          Review Exercise                                                 301

                         GRID                                                          302-303
                         MODEL QUESTION                                                   304]]></page><page Index="6"><![CDATA[Unit



                                                1























                     WE, OUR COMMUNITY


                                  AND NATION














                               Learning Achievements



                Explain the concept of development and federal state,
                Define development and explain the infrastructure of development like
                drinking water, electricity, human resources, its importance and the
                condition of development, and

                Find out the development activities carried out in our country and also its
                present condition.








            6   SOCIAL STUDIES - GRADE 8]]></page><page Index="7"><![CDATA[Lesson

                1                           DEVELOPMENT
































            The act  or process of growing or progressing is known as development.
            Everything  around us is growing or changing constantly.  The world has
            developed in various sectors like technology, medicine, farming, communication
            etc. Similarly, the society where we are living is changing and developing too.
            We are no longer living in the primitive society. The journey of the society from
            primitive age to the modern age is an example of development.

            Development is the constant positive change occurring in the society. It is a
            continuous process which helps to lead a society forward and become more
            advanced. Depending on various factors, the development process can be fast
            or slow but it never stops. Hardworking, honest and active human resources can
            speed up the development of a society. The people of developed societies are
            educated, skilled, healthy and satisfied. They are the human resources of that
            nation. The development of a nation depends heavily on its human resources.

            A society needs to utilize its means and resources effectively and efficiently
            in order to facilitate  the process of development.  Supply of raw materials,
            manpower  and  finance  which  can  be  utilized  effectively  and  help  in  the
            development process are called resources. These resources can be divided into
            three categories:

                                                                 SOCIAL STUDIES - GRADE 8    7]]></page><page Index="8"><![CDATA[a) Natural resources         b) Human resources          c) Financial resources

            a)  Natural resources:  The resources which
                are gifted by nature  are known as natural
                resources.  Water, air, herbs, sunlight,
                geographical  feature, hills, mountains,
                minerals,  etc  are  the  examples  of  natural
                resources.

            b)  Human resources: Every nation strives to
                educate  the  people  living  in  their  country
                in order to produce skilled and educated
                human  resource.  Human resources refer
                to manpower, intellectual ability, labor,
                skill, etc. Human resource is a major factor
                affecting the development of a country. The
                lack of human resource has been seen as the
                main reason of slow development in many
                countries.

            c)  Financial resources: Financial  resources
                mean the capital, currency, financial system,
                etc. It is also one of the major factors affecting
                the development process. The country which
                has a good financial status is developed more
                quickly  and  efficiently  compared  to  those
                countries whose financial status is weak. This is the factor which determines
                whether a country is developed, developing or under-developed. The ratio
                of financial activities increases with the rise in the income and expense level
                of the people. The financial activities set the pace of development in the
                society.
            If a nation is rich in resources then it can be developed. Stable government,
            honest politicians,  visionary  leaders  and commitment  are  some of the  other
            factors determining the smooth development of a country. Active participation
            of people is also required for the development of any country. They should
            be creative and hardworking. When all these factors come together and work
            harmoniously then only effective development is possible in any country.

            Note to  the  teacher:  Development can be defined as progress. It is possible to make the concept of
            development clear by involving students in activities like games, observations and discussions.
            8   SOCIAL STUDIES - GRADE 8]]></page><page Index="9"><![CDATA[Key Terms
            Commitment  : the state of being dedicated
            Constant       : something that does not change through time
            Financial Status : financial position or condition
            Pace           : the speed at which something happens
            Primitive      : very simple and not developed
            Strive         : to try very hard to do or get something
            Visionary      : having vision or foresight









                              Evaluation Exercises



            Activities

            1.  List down the changes that have come in the community where you live at
                present than that of past.
            2.  Read the following paragraph and prepare a dialogue putting forward your
                curiosity.

                      Export of electricity can change the future of Nepal

            Nepal is rich in water resources. The capacity for the production of electricity
            is estimated to be 83 thousand megawatt but we haven’t been able to produce
            even 2,000 megawatt of electricity. If we could manage to produce up to 10,000
            megawatt of electricity, then we could export it and become an economically
            strong nation. When will this dream of the nation come true?


            Very short answer questions
            1.  What is development?
            2.  What does a society need to speed up the development process?

            3.  Differentiate between human resources and natural resources in a sentence.
            4.  How does financial resource affect the development of a country?
            5.  What are the types of countries according to development status?
            6.  Define developed country.





                                                                 SOCIAL STUDIES - GRADE 8    9]]></page><page Index="10"><![CDATA[Short answer questions
            1.  How does development occur?
            2.  What should be done to make Nepal a developed country?

            3.  Write  down  the  different  types  of  resources  and  how  they  affect  the
                development process.
            4.  ‘If  a  nation  is  rich  in  resources  then  it  can  be  developed.’  Justify  this
                statement.
            5.  What do you mean by the active participation of people? Why is it important
                in the development of a country? Present your views.

            Look at the given pictures of the Karnali Bridge then and now; and find out
            the  differences  and  state  how  development  has  occurred  in  this  place  in
            these many years. Similarly make a list of changes seen in your society in last
            10 years.















































            10  SOCIAL STUDIES - GRADE 8]]></page><page Index="11"><![CDATA[Lesson

                2                          FEDERAL STATE




            Introduction

            Nepal had been practicing unitary system of government for a long decade.
            Under  unitary  system,  efforts  had  been  made  for  balanced  and  proportional

            development. But it failed to meet people’s expectation. Therefore, federalism
            was  raised as a political agenda against unitary system after the success of
            People’s Movement-II,  2062/063.  Federalism  was endorsed  by  the  second
            amendment of the Interim Constitution of Nepal 2063. The first meeting of the
            Constituent Assembly-I, which was held on 15  Jestha 2065 declared Nepal as
                                                             th
            “Federal Democratic Republican State”.

            Federal system is a political system in which a country is divided into different
            states  or provinces  with autonomous  power. Every  province  has  separate

            government along with its federal government at centre. Under federal system,
            there are three administrative units i.e. Central unit, Provincial unit and Local
            unit. The Central and Provincial unit has their own legislative, executive, and
            judicial bodies. Federalism is a principle which is similar throughout the world

            but its practice may differ according to the necessity of the country. The division
            of power between the federal and the state government is determined according
            to the clauses mentioned in the constitution.

            The Constitution of Nepal, has divided Nepal into 7 provinces and distributed

            the state power to central, provincial and local units. Some of them are presented
            below:

                  Federal Powers            Provincial Powers        Powers of Local Level
                Protection of national    State civil service         Municipal police
                unity and territorial       and other                 Cooperatives
                integrity                   government                FM operation

                Relating to national        services                  Local development
                security                                              projects and programs



                                                                 SOCIAL STUDIES - GRADE 8    11]]></page><page Index="12"><![CDATA[Central planning,           State level               Basic and secondary
                central bank, finance       electricity, irrigation   education

                policies, monetary          and water supply          Basic health sanitation
                and banking,                services, navigation      Distribution of land,
                monetary policies,          State universities,       building ownership
                foreign grants, aid         higher education,         certificates
                and loans                   libraries, museums        Drinking water, small
                Foreign and                 Matters relating to       electricity projects,
                diplomatic affairs,         the State Assembly,       alternative energy

                international relations     State Council of          Preservation and
                and United Nations          Ministers                 development of
                related matters             Intra-State trade,        language, culture and
                National                    State highways,           arts

                transportation              Health services           Local tax
                policies, management        Management of
                of railways and             lands, land records
                national highways

            In  federal  system,  if  the  state  government  is  found  to  be  ineffective  and

            unsuccessful  or if  national  emergency  is declared,  the  federal  government
            controls and directs  the concern  states until  other necessary arrangement  is
            made.

            There are various political systems practiced in the world. They are not perfect
            in themselves. Every political system has its merits and challenging factors.

            Merits of federal system

                 Maintains close relation between the state and its people,
                 Optimum use of means and resources,

                 Conflict may settle at local level,
                 Wide public participation in government activities,

                 Preservation of local arts, culture and heritages,
                 Decentralization of power,

                 Acceleration of development works,


            12  SOCIAL STUDIES - GRADE 8]]></page><page Index="13"><![CDATA[Maintain balanced population distribution,

                 Less dependency on central government.

            Challenging factors of federal system

                 Conflict between the states in regards of using natural resources of border
                areas,

                 Expensive form of government,
                 Misunderstanding may arise between central and state government regarding
                the sharing of power and authority,

                 Difficult to address the needs and demands of every minority,
                 Dangers of division or disintegration,

                 Unequal distribution of wealth,
                 Challenge to maintain equal recognition to all cultural groups.



























             Key Terms
            Acceleration   : speeding up, increase of speed
            Autonomous     : having the freedom to govern itself or control its own affairs
            Clauses        : a distinct provision in a document
            Decentralization : the distribution of power from a central authority to regional and local
                            authorities
            Disintegration  : fragmentation
            Merits         : good quality, value or worth

            Note to the teacher: Explain to the students the concept of federalism practically rather than theoretically.

                                                                 SOCIAL STUDIES - GRADE 8    13]]></page><page Index="14"><![CDATA[Evaluation Exercises



            Activity


            Find  the countries that have federal  system of  government from different
            sources and discuss their present situation.



            Very short answer questions

            1.  What is federal system?

            2.  What do you mean by decentralization?

            3.  When was Nepal declared as ‘Federal Democratic Republican State?

            4.  What are the different administrative units under federal system?
            5.  Into how many provinces has Nepal been divided?

            6.  When was Federalism implemented in Nepal?



            Short answer questions

            1.  Mention the importance of federalism.

            2.  Mention the structure of the federal system of government of Nepal.

            3.  Write  down  three  powers  each  of  federal,  provincial  and  local  units  of
                governance have according to our constitutional provision.

            4.  List out the merits and challenging factors of federal system.






















            14  SOCIAL STUDIES - GRADE 8]]></page><page Index="15"><![CDATA[Lesson

                3                          OUR PROVINCES




                                                                           D  I  A
                                                                        N
                                                                      I
                                N                                                  A

                                                         Province: 1  A          Biratnagar
                               Provincial Map of Nepal





                                                   Bagmati Province  N    Janakpur  Province: 2  I







                                         Gandaki Province  I          Hetauda







                                                         Pokhara  NAWAL PARASI  EAST  D  K  - Kathmandu  B  - Bhaktapur  L  - Lalitpur

                                                                  NAWAL   PARASI   WEST
                               Karnali Province  H                  RUPANDEHI







                                                   WEST  EAST  Deukhuri  Lumbini Province


                          C
                                                    Birendranagar  N             Provincial Headquarters

                                                                         Scale- 1:1,000,000


                                                 Godawari
                               A
                                           Sudurpashchim Province  I  D  N  I  KANCHANPUR  I



                                                                 SOCIAL STUDIES - GRADE 8    15]]></page><page Index="16"><![CDATA[Province No. 1

























































              Sudurpashchim   Province
                Province
                      Karnali
 Places
                            Gandaki
 Peak, Pass                 Province
 Airport            Lumbini Province  Bagmati
                                  Province
                                         Province
 Temple                          Province No. 2  No. 1
 Gompa
                Location of Province No. 1
 Chorten
 River
 Lake
 District Headquarters
            16  SOCIAL STUDIES - GRADE 8]]></page><page Index="17"><![CDATA[Province No. 1


            It lies in the eastern  part  of Nepal  and                Province No: 1
            covers mountain, hill and  Terai region.  Area                17.6% (25, 905 sq. km.)
            Mt. Sagarmatha,  Mt. Kanchanjunga,                            17.12% (4,534,943
            Mt. Makalu, etc  lie  in this  province.        Population    according to census
                                                                          2068 BS)
            Sagarmatha      National    Park,    Makalu                   14 (Taplejung, Panchthar,
            Barun National  Park, Kanchanjungha                           Ilam, Sankhuwasabha,

            Conservation  Area also lie here. Rivers        No. of Dis tricts  Tehrathum, Dhankuta,
                                                                          Bhojpur, Khotang,
            like Mechi,  Tamor,  Arun, etc have been                      Solukhumbu,
            supplying water in this province for various                  Okhaldhunga, Udayapur,
                                                                          Jhapa, Morang, Sunsari)
            purposes.
                                                                          137 (Rural Municipalities:
            Sherpa, Chhetri, Brahmin, Meche, Koche,  No. of Local         88, Municipalities: 46,
                                                                          Sub-Metropolitan Cities:
            Rajbansi, Lepcha, Limbu, Rai, etc are the       Levels        2 and Metropolitan
            main habitants. Barahakshetra, Pathibhara,                    City:1)

            Halesi Mahadev, Chhintang Devi, etc are         Headquarters  Biratnagar
            the major religious sites.

            Food crops like  paddy, maize,
            wheat, etc and cash crops like jute,
            tea,  sugarcane, tobacco, etc  are
            produced here.  This province has
            more agricultural region. Biratnagar,
            Ilam,     Dharan,      Okhaldhunga,

            Gaighat, etc  are the main  trade
            centers.      Similarly,     tourism,           Mt. Sagarmatha (8848.86 m)
            agriculture,  trade,  service,  etc  are
            the  major  economic  activities  in
            this province. Mahendra highway,
            Mechi highway, etc run through this
            province.  This province’s literacy

            rate is high due to the establishment
            of  Purbanchal  University  and
            many other important educational
            institutions in its various region.
                                                                  Halesi Mahadev


                                                                 SOCIAL STUDIES - GRADE 8    17]]></page><page Index="18"><![CDATA[Province No. 2























                               Province   No. 1


                             Bagmati   Province  Province No. 2


                         Gandaki  Province  Location of Province No. 2


                    Karnali  Province  Lumbini Province



                        Sudurpashchim
                        Province


            18  SOCIAL STUDIES - GRADE 8]]></page><page Index="19"><![CDATA[Province No. 2


            It lies in the middle Terai region of the                 Province No: 2
            country. It  has more  cultivable  land       Area          6.56% (9,661 sq. km.)
            compared to other provinces. To the north     Population    20.4% (5,404,145
                                                                        according to census
            of this province, there lies a dense forest                 2068 BS)

            in Chure range.                                             8 (Saptari, Siraha, Dhanusa,
                                                          No. of Dis tricts  Mahottari, Sarlahi,
            The  majority of population  belongs to                     Rautahat, Bara, Parsa)
                                                                        136 (Rural Municipalities:
            Madhesi  community. Yadav,  Tharu,  No. of Local            59, Municipalities: 73,
            Dalit, Muslim, etc are the castes and         Levels        Sub-Metropolitan Cities: 3
                                                                        and Metropolitan City: 1)
            ethnic  groups living in this province.       Headquarters  Janakpur
            The  languages spoken here  are  Nepali,
            Bhojpuri, Maithili,  Bajjika,  etc.  The
            religious sites such as Ram Janaki temple,
            Chhinnamasta temple, Gadhimai temple,

            etc are located here.

            Industrial  products,  fishery,  agricultural
            products, etc are contributing a lot in the            Ram Janaki Temple
            GDP  of  Nepal.  Birgunj,  a  gateway  of
            the country for foreign trade also lies in

            this province which collects  the highest
            revenue in the country. Janakpur, Simara,
            Chandranigahapur, Lahan, Rajbiraj,  etc
            are the important trade centers of this
            province.  Parsa  Wildlife Reserve  and a
            part  of Koshi  Tappu  Wildlife  Reserve           Koshi Tappu Wildlife Reserve

            are also contributing in the conservation
            of wildlife and for tourism development.
            Agriculture,  tourism, service,  trade,
            manufacturing,  etc  are the major
            occupation of this province. Construction

            and  operation  of  railway  certainly  be
            helpful  to improve  the life  standard of
            people in this province.                                Janakpur Railway

                                                                 SOCIAL STUDIES - GRADE 8    19]]></page><page Index="20"><![CDATA[Bagmati Province

























                               Province   No. 1


                             Bagmati   Province  Province No. 2


                         Gandaki  Province  Location of Bagmati Province


                    Karnali  Province  Lumbini Province



                        Sudurpashchim
                        Province


            20  SOCIAL STUDIES - GRADE 8]]></page><page Index="21"><![CDATA[Bagmati Province                                     Bagmati Province

                                                   Area          13.79% (20,300 sq. km.)
            Most part of this province is hilly    Population    20.87% (5,529,452 according to
            and mountainous. Gaurishankar,                       census 2068 BS)
            Langtang, Jugal, Ganesh, etc are                     13 (Dolakha, Ramechhap, Sindhuli,
                                                                 Kavrepalanchok, Sindhupalchok,
            the important mountains present        No. of Dis tricts  Rasuwa, Nuwakot, Dhading,
            in this province. Rivers like                        Chitwan, Makawanpur, Bhaktapur,
                                                                 Lalitpur, Kathmandu)
            Trishuli, Bagmati,  Bhotekoshi,        No. of Local   119 (Rural Municipalities: 74,

            etc are source of water for various  Levels          Municipalities: 41, Sub-Metropolitan
                                                                 Cities: 1 and Metropolitan City: 3)
            purposes.                              Headquarters  Hetauda

            Bhote and Sherpa are the main inhabitants of mountain
            region  whereas  Newars  are  the  major  inhabitants  of
            the  Kathmandu  valley.  Tharu,  Magar,  Tamang,  Jirel,
            Brahmin, Chhetri, Dashnami, Dalit, etc are living in
            different parts of the province. Palanchowk Bhagawati,

            Dakshinkali, Dolakha Bhimeshwor, Bauddhanath Stupa,
            Budhanilakantha,      Swayambhunath,       Pashupatinath,
            Gosainkunda, etc are the major religious sites located
            here. Reconstruction of some historical monuments like
            Rani Pokhari, Dharahara, old palaces and temples has           Newly Constructed
                                                                              Dharahara
            added an attraction for tourists.

            It has advanced in the educational sector,
            excavation  of mines,  tourism  industries,

            etc.      Commercialized         agriculture,
            more  opportunity  for employment  and
            important  trade centers have contributed               Langtang Mountain
            a large portion in the GDP of the country.
            Industrial  estates  like  Balaju,  Hetauda
            and Patan  are  in this province.  The
            major trade centers of this province are

            Kathmandu, Bhaktapur, Lalitpur, Banepa,
            Hetauda,     Chitwan,      Dhulikhel,     etc.
            Agriculture, tourism, trade, manufacturing,
            service, etc are the major occupation of the
            people.                                              Reconstructed Rani Pokhari

                                                                 SOCIAL STUDIES - GRADE 8    21]]></page><page Index="22"><![CDATA[Gandaki Province

























                               Province   No. 1


                             Bagmati   Province  Province No. 2


                         Gandaki  Province  Location of Gandaki Province


                    Karnali  Province  Lumbini Province



                        Sudurpashchim
                        Province


            22  SOCIAL STUDIES - GRADE 8]]></page><page Index="23"><![CDATA[Gandaki Province                                     Gandaki Province

            Most of this province  is hilly        Area          14.61% (21,504 sq. km.)
            and  mountainous.  The  mountain  Population         9.07% (2,403,757 according to
                                                                 census 2068 BS)
            valleys like Manang and Mustang                      11 (Gorkha, Lamjung, Tanahun, Kaski,
            also  lie  in  this  province.  Lumle,  No. of Dis tricts  Manang, Mus tang, Parbat, Syangja,
            a  place  receiving  highest  rainfall               Myagdi, Baglung, Nawalparasi Eas t)
            in the country and  Dana  gorge,  No. of Local       85 (Rural Municipalities: 58,
                                                                 Municipalities: 26, Sub-Metropolitan
            the world’s deepest gorge are also     Levels        Cities: 0 and Metropolitan City: 1)
            located in this province. The rivers  Headquarters   Pokhara
            like Kaligandaki, Marsyandi, Seti
            and their tributaries flow through this province.
            Dhaulagiri, Manaslu, Hiunchuli,  Annapurna,
            Machhapuchchhre, etc are the major mountain
            peaks  of  this  province.  Lakes  like  Tilicho,
            Phewa, Rupa, Begnas, etc have added natural
            beauty to this province.
            Magar, Gurung, Brahmin,  Thakali,  Chhetri,
            Dura, etc  are  the  main  inhabitants  of this
            province.  Pokhara  University  and various          Machhapuchchhre Mountain
            educational  institutions  have been providing
            educational opportunity here and have increased
            literacy  rate. Galeshwar, Baglung Kalika,
            Mutkinath, Rishikesh Temple, Bindyawasini,
            Manakamana,  Talbarahi, Dhorbarahi, etc
            are the major religious sites of this province.
            Development of infrastructures like cable car,
            airport, stadium, etc has increased much hopes             Pokhara Stadium
            in people for the development.
            There  is a great  possibility  of tourism
            development  in this province.  Pokhara,
            Bandipur,         Gorkha,         Manakamana,
            Muktinath,  etc are the tourist centers  in this
            province.  Kaligandaki  and  Marsyandi  river
            hydroelectricity  projects  are  producing  and
            supplying electricity in good amount. Foreign
            employment, tourism, agriculture, service, etc
            are the major occupation of people. Production           Manakamana Temple
            of apple in the mountain region and coffee in the hilly region has made this
            province popular.

                                                                 SOCIAL STUDIES - GRADE 8    23]]></page><page Index="24"><![CDATA[Province   No. 1



                                 Bagmati   Province  Province No. 2

                             Gandaki  Province  Location of Lumbini Province


                        Karnali  Province  Lumbini Province



                            Sudurpashchim
                            Province






                Lumbini Province















































            24  SOCIAL STUDIES - GRADE 8]]></page><page Index="25"><![CDATA[Lumbini Province


            There is no mountain range in                        Lumbini Province
            this province.  Most part  of this     Area          15.14% (22,288 sq. km.)
            is in Terai region and rest in hilly   Population    16.98% (4,499,272 according to
                                                                 census 2068 BS)
            region.  It  consists of plenty  of                  12 (Nawalparasi Wes t, Rupandehi,
            cultivable land. River Tinau, River    No. of Dis tricts  Kapilbas tu, Palpa, Arghakhanchi,
                                                                 Gulmi, Rukum Eas t, Rolpa, Pyuthan,
            Rapti, River Badhigad, etc are                       Daang, Banke, Bardiya)
                                                                 109 (Rural Municipalities: 73,
            the  major rivers in this province.  No. of Local    Municipalities: 32, Sub-Metropolitan
            Satyawati lake, Barakune lake and      Levels        Cities: 4 and Metropolitan City: 0)
            Jagdishpur lake lie here. Likewise,    Headquarters  Deukhuri
            Dang, Deukhuri, Rampur, Madi valleys

            are also located in this province.

            Magar, Tharu, Brahmin, Chhetri, etc are
            the  main  inhabitants  in this province.
            There  is a dense settlement  of Madhesi
            Community  in  its  southern  part.

            Bageswari, Thakurdwara,  Swargadwari,                      River Tinau
            Bhairabsthan, Resunga, Ridi, Lumbini,
            etc are the major religious sites located in
            this province.

            There is higher possibility of agricultural

            development.  Some important irrigation
            projects  are ongoing in this province.
            Irrigation  projects  like  Sikta,  Babai,
            Badganga, Tinau, etc have been assisting                    Lumbini
            in the increase of agricultural productions.
            Butwal,     Bhairahawa,      Krishnanagar,

            Tansen, Lamahi, Nepalgunj, Kohalpur, etc
            are the important trade centers located in
            this province. Nepal Sanskrit University,
            Lumbini Bauddha University have been
            established here.
                                                                  Swargadwari Temple


                                                                 SOCIAL STUDIES - GRADE 8    25]]></page><page Index="26"><![CDATA[Karnali Province













































                           Province   No. 1



                         Bagmati   Province  Province No. 2

                     Gandaki  Province  Location of Karnali Province



                Karnali  Province  Lumbini Province


                     Sudurpashchim
                    Province


            26  SOCIAL STUDIES - GRADE 8]]></page><page Index="27"><![CDATA[Karnali Province


            This province is located in the                      Karnali Province
            mountain and hilly region of mid-      Area          19.01% (27,984 sq. km.)
            western part of the country. Here,     Population    5.92% (1,570,418 according to
                                                                 census 2068 BS)
            the climate is dry and cold. Rivers                  10 (Rukum Wes t, Salyan, Dolpa,
            like Tila, Bheri, Sani Bheri, Humla    No. of Dis tricts  Jumla, Mugu, Humla, Kalikot,
                                                                 Jajarkot, Dailekh, Surkhet)
            Karnali,  etc are  providing water     No. of Local   79 (Rural Municipalities: 54,

            for irrigation and other purposes.  Levels           Municipalities: 25, Sub-Metropolitan
                                                                 Cities: 0 and Metropolitan City: 0)
            Similarly,      mountains        like  Headquarters  Birendranagar
            Kanjirowa,  Patarasi,  etc  and  the
            lakes like Rara, Phoksundo lie here. It consists

            of a large forest area, wide grasslands suitable
            for cattle rearing and medicinal herbs.

            People belonging to Thakuri, Chhetri, Brahmin,
            Dalit caste and ethnic groups live here. Kankre
            Bihar, Shey-gumba, Chandannath, Deuti Bajai,

            etc  are the  important  religious  sites  located         Phoksundo Lake
            here.

            This province has a higher possibility  of
            hydroelectricity     production.    The     wide
            grasslands are  suitable  for cattle  rearing  and

            production  of  medicinal  herbs.  Collection
            of  Yarsagumba and other medicinal  herbs,
            production  of apple,  walnut,  etc  are  the             Deuti Bajai Temple
            major  occupation  of  the  people  living  in
            mountain  region.  Ratna  highway, Karnali
            highway, Chhinchu  Jajarkot  road,  etc  have

            made great change in the transportation
            sector of this province. Jumla, Salli Bazar,
            Dailekh, Chhinchu, Birendranagar, etc are the
            major  trade  centers  located  here. Rara Lake,
            Phoksundo Lake,  Shey-Phoksundo National                  Rara National Park

            Park, Rara National Park, etc are the attractive tourist destinations here.

                                                                 SOCIAL STUDIES - GRADE 8    27]]></page><page Index="28"><![CDATA[Sudurpashchim Province






























































                                                            Sudurpashchim   Province
                                                              Province
                                                                    Karnali

                                                                          Gandaki
                                                                         Province
                                                                                Bagmati
                                                                  Lumbini Province
                                                                                Province
                                                                                       Province
                                                                                       No. 1
                                                                              Province No. 2
                                                           Location of Sudurpashchim Province
            28  SOCIAL STUDIES - GRADE 8]]></page><page Index="29"><![CDATA[Sudurpashchim Province
            This province is located in the far-               Sudurpashchim Province
            western  part  of  the  country.  The   Area          13.27% (19,539 sq. km.)

            recently  released  map  of Nepal  Population         9.63% (2,552,517 according to
                                                                  census 2068 BS)
            has covered Limpiyadhura and                          9 (Bajura, Bajhang, Doti, Achham,
            Lipulek in this province. Southern      No. of Dis tricts  Darchula, Baitadi, Dadeldhura,
            part of it is affected by the hot wind                Kanchanpur, Kailali)
            called ‘Loo’ during summer. There       No. of Local   88 (Rural Municipalities: 54,

            is enough rainfall  during winter  Levels             Municipalities: 33, Sub-Metropolitan
                                                                  Cities: 1 and Metropolitan City: 0)
            caused  by the  winter  monsoon.        Headquarters  Godawari
            Sub-tropical evergreen forest in the
            south, deciduous forest in the middle and alpine
            forest in the north are found here. This province
            consists of three geographical  regions: mountain
            region, hilly region and Terai region. Api and Saipal
            are the popular mountains of this province.
            People belonging to Brahmin,  Thakuri, Chhetri,                Api Mountain
            Tharu, Dalit etc caste and ethnic groups are the
            main  inhabitants  of this province.  Badhimalika,
            Shaileshwari, Urgatara,  etc are the important
            religious sites located here. This province is rich
            in culture. Gaura Parva and Deuda dance are the
            typical  culture of this province  but are popular
            throughout the country.                                 Shuklaphanta National Park

            There  is  sufficient  production  of  food  crops  in  this  province.  Paddy,  wheat,
            millet,  barley, maize,  oilseed, etc are produced in large volume.  Tanakpur
            barrage and Pancheshwar multipurpose  project  are the ongoing project, and
            West Seti, a project of national pride is also going to be implemented here soon.
            Shuklaphanta and Khaptad National Parks are added attraction for the tourists.
            Dadeldhura, Sanphebagar, Tikapur, Attariya, Silgadhi, Dhangadhi, Bhimdutta
            Nagar, etc  are the major trade  centers  located  in this province. Agriculture,
            service, trade, tourism, etc are the main economic activities of the people but
            still many people from here go to India for employment.

             Key Terms
            Destination : the place to which someone or something is going or being sent
            Excavation  : act of making hollow by removing the inner part
            Fishery    : the occupation or industry of catching or rearing fish
            Plenty     : sufficient
            Note to the teacher: Make the students share information regarding geological condition of the provinces
            where they come from. And also give them the knowledge regarding the other provinces.

                                                                 SOCIAL STUDIES - GRADE 8    29]]></page><page Index="30"><![CDATA[Evaluation Exercises



            Activities

            1.  Read the list given below and draw a pie chart showing the area of seven
                provinces:
                Province No. 1                                       25,905 sq. km.
                Province No. 2                                       9,661 sq. km.

                Bagmati Province                                     20,300 sq. km.
                Gandaki Province                                     21,504 sq. km.
                Lumbini Province                                     22,288 sq. km.

                Karnali Province                                     27,984 sq. km.
                Sudurpashchim Province                               19,539 sq. km.

            2.  Mark the seven provinces in the map of Nepal and indicate each province
                with a different colour.


            Very short answer questions
            1.  When was Nepal divided into seven Provinces?
            2.  Name any two pilgrimage sites of Province No. 1.

            3.  List the cash crops grown in Province No. 2.
            4.  Name two religious places of Bagmati Province.
            5.  Which two dry valleys lie in Gandaki Province?

            6.  Which national parks are located in Karnali Province?
            7.  Mention any two major trade centres of Lumbini Province.
            8.  Name two mountains of Sudurpashchim Province.

            9.  Why does rainfall take place in winter in Sudurpashchim Province?
            Short answer questions
            1. What are the major attractions of Province No. 1?

            2. What are the religious sites and major tourist attractions of Bagmati
               Province?
            3. Province No. 2 consists of more cultivable land compared to other provinces.
               How should it be utilized to get more benefits? Present your views.
            4. ‘Gandaki Province has great prospect of tourism.’ Justify the statement.

            5. Why is density of population low in Karnali Province? Give reasons.
            30  SOCIAL STUDIES - GRADE 8]]></page><page Index="31"><![CDATA[Lesson

                4                        DRINKING WATER




            Sanjeev Singh lives in Banke. Hand pump
            is the main source of water in his home. So
            there is no scarcity of water. But the water
            smells  bad  sometimes.  Sanjeev  has heard
            about harmful chemical  called arsenic
            which is present in the water obtained from
            hand pump and can cause skin disease. But
            he has no other option and his family  is
            compelled to drink that water.                             Hand Pump
            Khagendra lives in Kathmandu. There is a water tap in his home but water flow
            is not regular in this water tap. Sometimes he has to wake up as early at 1 am in
            the morning to collect water. In the dry seasons, he has to buy drinking water
            from tanker or jar.

            Tashi lives in Namche Bazar. He uses a pond near his home as source of water.
            He does not need to go far to bring drinking water but the animals go there
            time and often, some people throw garbage over there and pollute the water.
            When people drink such polluted water, they suffer from various water-borne
            diseases like cholera, dysentery, diarrhea, typhoid, jaundice and other contagious
            diseases.

            Shanti Maya lives in a village of Panchthar district. There are no sources of
            water near her home. Every day she has to wake up early in the morning to fetch
            water from the river. It takes about three hours to fetch drinking water from the
            river. These are some examples of how people of Nepal are facing the drinking
            water problems.

            Water is one of the most important basic needs for all the living being. About 70%
            of the human body is made up of water. Human beings can live without food for
            some time but not without water. Water is used for various purposes, such as for
            cooking food, washing clothes, taking bath, growing crops, construction work
            and for generating hydro-electricity. Water plays a vital role in the development
            of a country. Clean drinking water is necessary for good health. If the citizens
            are healthy, development of a country will be rapid. Thus, government should
            make all the efforts to supply pure drinking water to its citizens.

                                                                 SOCIAL STUDIES - GRADE 8    31]]></page><page Index="32"><![CDATA[Supply of Drinking Water in Nepal

                                                     No. of family/household
              S.N.   Sources of Drinking water                                    Percentage
                                                            using water

               1.   Tap or piped water                       2,591,379               53.36
               2.   Covered well/Kuwa                         132,870                 2.74
               3.   Hand pump                                1,904,965               39.23
               4.   River/Stream                              60,580                  1.25
               5.   Water from other sources                  132,551                 2.73

               6.   Not stated                                33,900                  0.69
                                 Total                       4,856,245                100

                                                           Source: Central Bureau of Statistics, 2068 BS

            Problems of drinking water in Nepal
                 Half of the total population is deprived of pure and safe drinking water.

                 In some areas of hilly region, the source of water is very far and limited.
                 Presence of arsenic in the tube-well water in Terai region.

                 Pollution due to lack of awareness among the people.
                 Lack of sources of water in urban areas.

                 Difficult topography to run drinking water project.
            Above mentioned problems have been creating hurdles to supply pure and safe

            drinking water in our country. The government has to carry out effective plans
            to rectify the drinking water related problems.

            Solutions
                 The water resources should be conserved and kept clean.

                 Use drinking water after purity test only.
                 Make arrangement of drinking water with the coordination of government

                sector and local community.
                 Use boiled and filtered water for drinking.
                 Reservoirs of drinking water should be cleaned time to time.

                 Make provisions to fulfill the demands of drinking water in urban areas.

                 Launch  awareness  among  the  people  regarding  the  proper  use  of  water
                without wasting it.
            32  SOCIAL STUDIES - GRADE 8]]></page><page Index="33"><![CDATA[There  are  many  places  in  Nepal

            where people have to walk for
            miles  to get  drinking  water.  The
            government should try to supply

            water to every home. A lot of time
            and hard work is wasted on trying
            to get drinking water. If this facility
            can be more accessible, then people
            will have more time and energy to

            use in more beneficial work. The problem is more complex in the cities. There
            aren’t enough public taps for the people and even if there are, then there is no
            water supply in those taps. People stay for hours on queue to get one bucket of

            water. The supply of water always falls short and people go home disappointed.
            This situation needs to be changed. In Terai region people have started relying
            on underground source of water. But this water contains harmful chemical called
            arsenic. We should not drink water containing this chemical as it is hazardous to
            our health. The tube-wells and the taps are marked with red signs which indicate

            that the water contains arsenic.

            The Constitution  of Nepal has also made a provision in fundamental  rights
            as “Each citizen shall have the right to access to clean water and hygiene”.

            Ongoing Melamchi Water Supply Project has also been giving finishing touch
            to the project in Kathmandu valley. This project aims at providing safe and
            quality drinking water to the people of the Kathmandu valley.





             Key Terms
            Compelled  : forced to do something
            Contagious : capable of transmitting disease
            Deprived  : lacking a specified benefit that is considered important
            Fetch      : go for and then bring back
            Scarcity   : shortage or short supply
            Vital      : important

            Note to the teacher:  Make the students participate in role plays and make them visit places to raise
            awareness and get involved in programs regarding the sources and sensible use of water.

                                                                 SOCIAL STUDIES - GRADE 8    33]]></page><page Index="34"><![CDATA[Evaluation Exercises



            Activities

            1.  Draw any source of water and present its usefullness in class.

            2.  Read the notice given by the Drinking Water Supply Cooperation below and
                discuss how water can be used in a proper manner and present in class.

                      Request from Drinking Water Supply Cooperation

            You can save a person’s life by just saving a glass of water. Hence, please give
            your attention towards the following points:
                 Make the habit of closing the tap after use.

                 Don’t leave the tap open while being busy in other works.
                 Put the nozzle on the tap.

                 Don’t use drinking water for irrigation.

                 Use rain water to wash clothes and for cleaning purpose.
                 Don’t drink water directly from the source. Filter it, add medicine, perform
                SODIS or boil it before drinking.

                 It’s not enough for the water to be decontaminated. We have to make sure
                that the vessels that we use to store water, the area where we fill water
                from and our hands are clean too. If we don’t pay attention to this then the
                water might get contaminated and we may fall sick.

                 We should make sure that the source of water is clean.
                 Make sure that the water tap is accessible to disabled people as well as the
                children.


            Very short answer questions

            1.  What is arsenic?
            2.  For what purposes is water used?

            3.  How do sources of water get polluted?
            4.  List out two water borne diseases.

            5.  What are the sources of water?
            6.  Why is the demand of water growing in Nepal?

            34  SOCIAL STUDIES - GRADE 8]]></page><page Index="35"><![CDATA[Short answer questions
            1.  List the importance of water in human life.

            2.  What is the current situation of water supply in Nepal? Explain.
            3.  Write a letter to the drinking water cooperation requesting them to check
                the water supply line since there is no water supply in the taps.
            4.  What are the problems of drinking water in Nepal? Suggest the possible
                measures to solve it.

            5.  Draw a pie-chart on the basis of the following data.
                                Supply of Drinking Water in Nepal

             S.N. Sources of Drinking water         No. of family/household using water


               1.         Tap or piped water                        2,591,379


               2.            Hand pump                              1,904,965

               3.               Others                               359,901


                                 Total                              4,856,245






































                                                                 SOCIAL STUDIES - GRADE 8    35]]></page><page Index="36"><![CDATA[Lesson

                5                                   ENERGY




            Electricity  is one of the most important
            sources of energy. Industrial development

            is not possible  without development  of
            electricity. Electricity  plays vital role in
            the modern world, we use electricity  for

            various  purposes. Refrigerator, fax,  oven,
            heater, rice  cooker, etc  can  be run by
            electricity. Industries require machinery                   Solar Panel
            and  other  heavy  tools  to  produce  many
            manufactured goods. Electricity is a must

            to run these machinery and heavy tools.

            We  get  these  energies  from  different
            sources like  generator, hydropower, solar

            power,  bio-gas,  woods, oil,  coal,  natural
            gas, windmill, batteries, water mill,  etc.
            We also get the energy from nuclear plant,               Hydro Power Dam
            petroleum,  biological  and farm waste

            material, etc.

            Energy plays an important role in our daily
            life. It is also needed for household work, to
            operate an office, to run medical equipment

            in hospitals, to run industries etc. For
            this reason energy has become one of the
            essential  parts of human  life.  Developed
            countries consume more energy. That’s why                    Windmill

            energy development is related to human peace and prosperity and economic
            development.



            36  SOCIAL STUDIES - GRADE 8]]></page><page Index="37"><![CDATA[Hydro-power was generated for the first time in Nepal in 1968 BS during the

            time of Chandra Shumsher in Pharping, south of Kathmandu. Pherping Hydro-
            power station’s capacity was 500 KW. The second hydro-power station was
            established in 1991 BS during the time of Juddha Shumsher at Sundarijal in the

            north of Kathmandu, having the capacity of 640 KW.

            There  is tremendous  potentiality  in Nepal for electricity  production.
            There  are  plenty  of  rivers  which  flow  continuously  throughout  the  year  in
            Nepal. It has the potential  of producing 83,000 mega watts hydropower.

            From the economic and technical  point of view around 43,000 mega watt
            hydropower can be produced. But till date only 1,000 mega watt hydropower
            has been produced. Majority of the power produced in Nepal has been utilized
            only in cities. There is still a shortage of power in the remote areas.


            The lack of sufficient amount of electricity has directly affected industries, trade,
            agriculture  sector, etc. After the completion  of some micro hydroelectricity
            projects, and control over leakage and widespread corruption in this field, the
            problem of power-cut has been gradually decreasing as well. We can minimize

            the problem of power shortage in the following ways:
                 Reduce the unnecessary use of electric power at home.

                 Make the public aware about proper use of electricity at home.

                 Use less electricity consuming appliances.
                 Turn off the switches of the used appliances after the use is over.

                 Use alternative sources of energy like solar power, bio-gas, wind power, etc.
                 Use bright colours or paints at home.





             Key Terms
            Bio-gas     : any gas fuel derived from the decay of organic matter
            Generator   : a dynamo or similar machine for converting mechanical energy into electricity
            Hydropower : electricity produced from machines that are run by moving water
            Solar power  : power obtained by harnessing the energy of the sun’s ray

            Note to the teacher:  Organize an educational tour in the places/community where renewable energy
            technology and micro hydro projects are being operated.

                                                                 SOCIAL STUDIES - GRADE 8    37]]></page><page Index="38"><![CDATA[Evaluation Exercises



            Activities

            1.  What would happen if there is no electricity?

            2.  What will happen if petrol, diesel, aviation fuel, kerosene and cooking gas
                are all used up by us?



            Very short answer questions
            1.  Write any four sources of energy.

            2.  Why is energy an essential part of human life?
            3.  Which is the first hydro-power project of Nepal? When was it established?

            4.  During whose reign Sundarijal Hydro-power Station established? Write its
                production capacity.
            5.  Mention any two effects of load-shedding.


            Short answer questions
            1.  Define energy and write its various sources.
            2.  What is the importance of energy? Make a list.

            3.  Write five solutions for the energy crisis of Nepal.
            4.  As  Nepal  is  rich  in  water  resources,  we  can  produce  plenty  of  hydro-

                electricity and export it to different countries for our economy benefits.
                What do you think need to be done to achieve this?
            5.  List the uses of electricity.

            6.  How can we minimize the problem of power shortage? Suggest the possible
                ways of solutions.

            Community Work


            Collect the list of different kinds of energy that has been used in your home,
            school or community. Also find out the uses of such energies.








            38  SOCIAL STUDIES - GRADE 8]]></page><page Index="39"><![CDATA[Lesson

                6                       HUMAN RESOURCE





























            The positive changes that  occur in an individual,  family, community  or a
            country as a whole is known as development. This is a constant and never ending
            process which had been going on in the past and will continue to go on in the
            future. There is a vast difference in the lifestyle and the living standard of our

            ancestors compared to our modern day lifestyle. This is the result of development.
            If there was no development, there would be no difference between the life we
            lead now and the life that our ancestors led years ago. Human resources play an
            important role in the social and economic development of a country.


            Human resources are those people who are educated, knowledgeable, skilled
            and experienced, physically healthy, mentally aware and are rational thinkers.
            Human resources are also known as manpower, labors or human capital. It can
            be divided into three groups:


            Unskilled      - The group of people who lack the skill and training are known as
                            unskilled human resource.

            Semi-skilled - The  group of people  who have  certain  skills  but still  not

                            qualified for a particular job is known as semi-skilled human
                            resource.

                                                                 SOCIAL STUDIES - GRADE 8    39]]></page><page Index="40"><![CDATA[Skilled        - The  group  of  people  who  are  well  qualified  and  trained  in  a

                            particular field is known as skilled.

            All these three categories are equally important for the development process.
            Human resources alone are not enough for the development process. The natural
            resources, financial resources and human resources have to come together and
            be utilized in a correct manner for development.


            A country  can  be considered  developed  only  when all  of its part  becomes
            developed. For the development of the health sector various professionals like
            woman health caretaker, rural health workers, health assistance and maternity
            health worker are required. Similarly, other required professionals are nurses,

            doctors, lab assistants, pharmacologists, administrative workers, etc.

            For the development of the agricultural sector, the required human resources
            are  farmers,  JTA, JT  and  laborers.  In  order  to  achieve  development  in  this
            area, the farmers have to be given enough knowledge and training to be able to

            understand the requirements of their field. If farmers are trained well, there is
            a good scope of agriculture in Nepal. The other types of activities can be fruit
            farming, vegetable farming, animal rearing, floral business, etc. It’s not only the
            agricultural sector or health sector but there is equal potential for the growth of

            other sectors like education, tourism, construction, transportation, media, etc.
            We need people having good knowledge and skills in their required fields for
            the proper development of these sectors.


            In the economical  context,  our country has produced professionals in
            agriculture,  trade  and  civil  services  but  we are still  lacking  in  professions
            like  medicine,  engineering,  media,  etc.  Due  to  this  lack,  the  speed  of  the
            development  process has been hindered.  The most important  factor  that
            we need to understand is that no profession is inferior or superior. Each and

            every profession has equal importance and contributes to the development of
            the country. We need to understand that and respect every profession without
            categorizing  them  into  any  levels.  It’s the  responsibility  of  the  citizens  to

            share their creativity, skill and knowledge honestly to help in the process of
            development. The government needs to give opportunity to the people to learn


            40  SOCIAL STUDIES - GRADE 8]]></page><page Index="41"><![CDATA[new skills and educate them in various areas to be able to make the country

            developed  as a whole. Knowledge and education  makes  a person creative,
            responsible, helpful, independent and rational.

            But Nepal is suffering from scarcity of human power needed for development.

            There are several problems of human resources in Nepal. Some of the problems
            are:

                 Lack of systematic production of manpower,
                 Lack of vocational and technical institutions,

                 Inequality between unskilled, semi-skilled and skilled human resources,
                 Lack of information about scopes, opportunities, possibilities, etc,

                 Lack of far sighted planning and policies,
                 Lack of skillful training and practical education system.

            It is necessary to develop in the area of science and technology for the economic

            development of the country. For this, our country is in need of professionals in
            this area. Ample training and opportunities should be provided to the people to
            develop in this area. The country should always depend on its own people to
            formulate and execute development plans.














             Key Terms
            Ample          : plenty
            Floral         : of flowers
            Hinder         : obstruct
            Pharmacologist : a specialist in the science of medications
            Potential      : showing the capacity to develop
            Rational       : logical thinking


            Note  to  the  teacher:  Make  the students discuss  about  the unskilled,  semi-skilled  and  skilled  human
            resource by showing them related charts and pictures.


                                                                 SOCIAL STUDIES - GRADE 8    41]]></page><page Index="42"><![CDATA[Evaluation Exercises



            Activity

            What types of human resources are present in your community? Make a list.




            Very short answer questions
            1.  What is development?

            2.  Define human resources.

            3.  List out the types of human resources.
            4.  What do you understand by skilled human resources?

            5.  Differentiate between unskilled and semi-skilled human resources.

            Short answer questions

            1.  What is the role of the people in the process of development?
            2.  What efforts have been made in Nepal to produce skilled human resource

                for the economic and social development of the country?
            3.  What kind of human resource do you want to be in future? Give reasons.

            4.  What are the ways to produce skilled human resource? Make a list.
            5.  Why is human resource important? Write in a paragraph.





























            42  SOCIAL STUDIES - GRADE 8]]></page><page Index="43"><![CDATA[Lesson                         DEVELOPMENT

                7                      PROJECTS OF NEPAL




            There are many projects being implemented for the development of areas like
            road, drinking water, communication,  electricity, sanitation,  education  and

            health in Nepal. Some of the projects have been completed while others are still
            in the process of completion. Some of the examples are given below:

            School Sector Development Plan 2016 - 2023:

            This project has been started with the vision to
            contribute to the development of self-sustainable,
            competitive,  innovative and value oriented
            citizens for the socioeconomic transformation of

            the nation. It has taken the mission to produce the
            needed human resources to elevate Nepal’s status
            from a Least Developed Country by 2022 and to
            reach the status of a middle-income country by

            2030. The total estimated cost of the seven-year                         Government of Nepal
                                                                                     Ministry of Education
            SSDP is US$ 10,577 million, of which $6,461                              October 2016
            million is estimated for the first five years (2016/17-2021/22).

            Upper       Tamakoshi       Hydropower

            Project:  This 456 megawatt project is
            funded by Nepal Electricity Authority,
            Nepal  Telecom,  Citizen  Investment
            Trust,    Rastriya     Bima     Sansthan,

            Employees  Provident  Fund, civil
            servants and general  public.  As this
            project is entirely financed by domestic
            funds, the electricity  produced by it will be comparatively  cheaper.  The

            hydroelectricity will be generated from River Tamakoshi at northern part of
            Dolakha district. The organization named, “Upper Tamakoshi Hydroelectricity
            Limited” has been established in 2063 BS to run the project.


                                                                 SOCIAL STUDIES - GRADE 8    43]]></page><page Index="44"><![CDATA[Pokhara Regional International  Airport: From this project,  it has been

            expected  that  Pokhara  Airport  will  be  upgraded  as Pokhara  Regional
            International Airport which will ultimately contribute for sustainable tourism
            development. The construction was formally started at Chhinedanda, Pokhara
            by placing the foundation stone on 1
                                                     st
            Baishakh 2073 BS and now it is under
            construction by Chinese Company.
            This  project’s completion  will  help  to

            develop Pokhara as one of the attractive
            tourist  destinations  of  the  world. After
            the  completion  of  this  project,  large
            aeroplanes up to 200 seats can take off
            and land on Pokhara Airport.

            Above mentioned projects are the representative projects of Nepal. There are
            several other projects of national glory. Some of the important projects are:

                Budhi Gandaki Hydro Power Project: It has the production capacity of
                1,200 MW (megawatt). It lies in between Gorkha and Dhading district.


                Puspalal Lokmarga (Madhya Pahadi Lokmarga): It connects east
                Chiyobhanjyang of Panchthar district to Jhulaghat of Baitadi district. It is
                1,776 km long.

                East-West Railway: It is also important project of national glory. It’s length
                is 950 km. It connects eastern most part to western most part of Nepal.

                Kathmandu Terai Madhes Fast Track: It is 76 km long fast track that
                connects Kathmandu with the Terai region.



             Key Terms
            Approximately : estimated
            Implemented  : put a plan into effect
            Innovative    : advanced
            Sanitation    : conditions relating to public health, especially the provision of clean drinking
                           water and adequate sewage disposal
            Ultimately    : finally
            Note to the teacher: Make the students collect articles that are published in various magazines regarding
            developmental programs going on in Nepal and discuss in class.
            44  SOCIAL STUDIES - GRADE 8]]></page><page Index="45"><![CDATA[Evaluation Exercises



            Activity

            Discuss with your group the advantages of developmental programs and come
            to a conclusion.


            Very short answer questions

            1.  What is project?
            2.  Write the main aims of Rural Water Supply and Sanitation Project.
            3.  What is the mission of School Sector Development Plan?

            4.  Who are funding in the Upper Tamakoshi Hydropower Project?
            5.  What is the main aim of Pokhara Regional International Airport Project?

            Short answer questions
            1.  Write down the main functions of western Nepal rural drinking water and
                sanitation project.

            2.  Mention the vision of the School Sector Development Plan.
            3.  How  does  School  Sector  Development  Plan  help  to  develop  education
                sector?
            4.  Make news article related to the developmental project in Nepal and its
                benefits.

            5.  What types of developmental activities are required in your community?


            Community Work

            Divide yourselves into groups and visit the places where developmental works
            are being conducted. Prepare a report based on your findings. If you are unable
            to visit the place then fix an appointment with an INGO or local social worker
            who  is involved in  such developmental  works.  Discuss  the activities  of  the
            Rural Municipality or INGO and the benefits the people are getting from such
            organizations.











                                                                 SOCIAL STUDIES - GRADE 8    45]]></page><page Index="46"><![CDATA[Review Exercise




            1.  Study the given table about the present situation and goal of fifteenth
                five year plan about the supply of drinking water and answer the given
                questions.

                                                              Present
                                                                                  Goal
                 S.N.             Particular                  situation       (2080/81 BS)
                                                            (2074/75 BS)
                       Total population benefited
                   1.  from basic level drinking water           88                 99
                       facilities (in %).
                       Total population benefited from
                   2.  middle/high quality drinking              20                 40
                       water facilities (in %).
                a)  What programs have to  be launched  to  increase  the basic  drinking
                    water facilities to all the citizens?

                b)  Is it possible to achieve the objective of high quality drinking water
                    facilities? Discuss in class.


            2.  Complete  the  following  table  with  the  help  of  text,  atlas  and  other

                reference materials.

                                    Trade     Tourism  Popular                   Agriculture
                    Province                                        Minerals
                                    Centre      Place     Things                 Productions













            3.  Write short notes on:
                a)  Importance of alternative energy

                b)  ‘Clean drinking water, healthy life’
                c)  Importance of skilled human resources



            46  SOCIAL STUDIES - GRADE 8]]></page><page Index="47"><![CDATA[Unit



                                                2























                        OUR SOCIAL NORMS


                                   AND VALUES














                               Learning Achievements



                Find out about Nepal’s social and religious practices and customs, and
                participate in their preservation,

                Recognize Nepal as a country of ‘unity in diversity’ and maintain its social
                harmony and tolerance,

                Identify the National Heritages of Nepal and help in conserving them, and
                Identify various International Personalities and get inspirations from their
                good works.







                                                                 SOCIAL STUDIES - GRADE 8    47]]></page><page Index="48"><![CDATA[Lesson              SOCIAL TRADITIONS AND

                1                      CUSTOMS OF NEPAL





            A class is going  on about  the  social  tradition  and customs  of Nepal.  In the
            presence of teacher, some students are presenting their understandings about
            the topic.











            Teacher               : Today we are going to discuss about traditions and
                                    customs of Nepal. As we know Nepal is a multi-religious,
                                    multi-lingual,  multi-cultural  and multi-ethnic  country,
                                    our customs and traditions differ from one part of Nepal
                                    to another. Each community  has its own tradition  and
                                    custom.  Like  wedding,  birth  and  death  rituals,  etc  in
                                    Nepal vary according to ethnic groups and castes. Now
                                    you tell about your own traditions and customs that you
                                    know.

            Srijana Shrestha  : I am going to talk about ‘Guthi’ which is prevalent in

                                    the Newar community. It is a social organization which
                                    maintains  the socio-economic order of Newar society.
                                    It  is  one  of  the  most  powerful  social  organizations  of
                                    Newars. It has been practiced from Lichchhavi period.
                                    Guthi plays an important role in preserving the culture,
                                    building and renovating the religious places, cremation
                                    of the dead, conducting funerals, etc. The members of the
                                    Guthi are known as the Guthiyaar and the eldest member
                                    of the  Guthi is known as  Thakali. The  responsibilities

                                    of the Guthi are distributed among the Guthiyaars. The
                                    popular  Guthis in the  newar community  are  Dewali
                                    Guthi, Sana Guthi, Si Guthi, etc.

            48  SOCIAL STUDIES - GRADE 8]]></page><page Index="49"><![CDATA[Prem Darlami          : In the Magar community, the organization which

                                    functions to gain the social objectives  is known as
                                    Bheja. It helps in performing religious festivals, rites and
                                    rituals, celebrations, traditional practices and agricultural
                                    works,  etc. It also helps in conducting economic
                                    activities and resource mobilization as well as keeps the
                                    community united. The leadership lies in the hands of the
                                    eldest member of the group and is known as Mukhiya.

                                    It is responsible to preserve the religious and traditional
                                    practices and it also appoints the pujari.

            Chaaya Chaudhary  : The Badghar tradition has been prevalent in the Tharu
                                    community  from the ancient  time.  The term  Badghar
                                    refers to the position of a village leader who leads his
                                    own village. Badghar’s role is like a chairman, judge and
                                    administrator in the village. The Badghar is responsible
                                    for maintaining the unity in the community, organizing

                                    the rituals relating to deaths and births, and controlling
                                    and conducting the social rules. Every year on the month
                                    of Magh the community appoints the Badghar.

            Anu Gurung            : Rodighar is a tradition of the Gurung community. The
                                    young boys and girls of this community get together at
                                    the Rodighar to dance and sing in the evening. It is an
                                    ideal institution for entertainment under the supervision

                                    of head of the family.  All the members of the  Rodhi
                                    usually work together in the field or go together to fetch
                                    woods from the forest. The Rodighar helps in making the
                                    relationship amongst the people of the community strong
                                    and harmonious. They also discuss and plan about the
                                    things that they will do the next day.

            Ishan Lamsal          : I am going to talk about ‘Parma’ and ‘Paincho’. These
                                    two traditions are not specific to any caste. It is common

                                    in all parts of Nepal. At first, I will tell you about ‘Parma’.
                                    It is a practice of giving and taking help especially in



                                                                 SOCIAL STUDIES - GRADE 8    49]]></page><page Index="50"><![CDATA[agricultural  activities.  When  the  farmers  need  help  to

                                    work  in  the  field,  they  call  their  neighbours  to  work
                                    for certain hours of the day in their field. In return, do
                                    the same for their neighbours. The practice of ‘Parma’
                                    is thus a system of supporting each other in work turn
                                    by turn collectively. It is also called Aalopalo Pratha in
                                    Nepalese society. Similarly, ‘Paincho’ is the system of
                                    giving and taking of something. It is related to goods.

                                    In this practice, people take the goods which they are in
                                    need from others and return it without any addition of
                                    interest or amount in due time. Such system is generally
                                    found in rural areas but nowadays, due to development of
                                    local shops and markets, it has been declining.

            Dipak Singh           : Dear friends, today I am going to tell you about ‘Dhikuti’.
                                    In common  sense,  Dhikuti means store room where

                                    various food grains are kept. But now it has been adopted
                                    in monetary matters. In this system, money is raised from
                                    the Dhikuti members to collect a fund for specific purpose
                                    periodically. The collected fund is used by its members
                                    turn by turn. After using the fund the members have to pay
                                    minimum interest rate. At present, this system is declared
                                    illegal by the government as there are more possibility of
                                    cheating and fraud.


            Teacher               : Thank you all for sharing your ideas and knowledge with
                                    your classmates.




             Key Terms
            Cremation  : funeral
            Mobilization : to put into active service
            Prevalent   : widespread
            Renovate    : repair, restore

            Note to the teacher:  As mentioned in the lesson, there might be certain social practices in the local
            community which has been contributing in the social, economical and cultural upliftment of that community.
            Find out about them and make the class discuss about its importance and conservation.
            50  SOCIAL STUDIES - GRADE 8]]></page><page Index="51"><![CDATA[Evaluation Exercises



            Activity

            Write a poem or make a poster titled ‘Social Traditions’ and display it in a notice
            or information board.



            Very short answer questions
            1.  In which community is ‘Guthi’ prevalent?
            2.  Who are Guthiyaar and Thakali?

            3.  What is Bheja?
            4.  What do you know about Mukhiya?
            5.  What is the role of Badghar in Tharu community?

            6.  When is Badghar appointed in Tharu community?
            7.  What is done at Rodhighar?
            8.  How does Rodhighar help in making the relationship amongst the people?

            9.  Differentiate between ‘Parma’ and ‘Paincho’.
            10. Why is Dhikuti declared illegal at present?

            Short answer questions
            1.  Write in brief about the importance of social tradition and customs.
            2.  Write down the differences and similarities between Bheja, Badghar and
                Guthi.

            3.  Explain the importance of Rodhighar in Gurung community in Nepal.
            4.  How  does  the  Rodhighar help  in  making the relationship  amongst the
                people of the community strong and harmonious?
            5.  “Parma and  Paincho are traditional  system of co-operation.” Justify the
                statement.


            Community Work

            Identify  and  find  out  about  your  social  traditions  and  customs  and  discuss
            about it in class.








                                                                 SOCIAL STUDIES - GRADE 8    51]]></page><page Index="52"><![CDATA[Lesson

                2                     RELIGIONS OF NEPAL




            An institutional  practice  of improving  habits and characters  for making  a
            better life is known as religion. Religion teaches us how to live our life with

            moral values. It guides us and shows us the way to control our weaknesses
            and improve our thinking and the way of living. There is religious tolerance
            among  the  various  religious  groups in  Nepal.  Religious  tolerance  is the

            system  of  respecting  all  religious  group  equally.  Everybody  participates  in
            each other’s religious activities. Nepal was declared a secular state on 4  Jestha,
                                                                                      th
            2063 BS and it is also recognized by the Constitution of Nepal. Secularism
            is the belief that religion should not play a role in government, education, or
            other public parts of society. The government is neutral in term of religion in

            secularism. The religions that are mainly practiced in Nepal are as follows:

            Hinduism

            Hinduism  is the  oldest  religion
            which has been followed since the
            ancient time. So it is called Sanatan
            religion. Hindu people believe that

            god  is  present  in  different  forms
            and  avatar. They  believe  that  our
            good deeds take  us to heaven
            whereas our bad deeds push us to

            hell. Hindu practices include daily                   Pashupatinath
            rituals such as puja and recitations,
            annual festivals  and occasional  pilgrimages.  It teaches  us to be truthful,
            sympathetic, helpful, honest, and possess good behavior. Pashupatinath is one

            of the most famous Hindu temples of Nepal. It attracts many pilgrims from
            various part of the world. The major religious books of Hinduism are Vedas,
            Puraan, Mahabharata, Ramayana, Geeta, etc. Dashain, Tihar, Chhath, Holi, etc
            are the main festivals observed by Hindus.


            52  SOCIAL STUDIES - GRADE 8]]></page><page Index="53"><![CDATA[Buddhism

            Lumbini  is the birth place  of

            Lord Buddha. It is in Rupandehi
            district,  Lumbini  Province  of
            Nepal. Buddha was born in 563
            BC. Buddhist people follow the
            teachings of Gautam Buddha.

            Buddhism is listed as the world’s
            fourth largest religion.  The  main
            teachings of Buddhism is to speak                        Lumbini

            the truth, say no to violence, don’t
            steal from others, follow good behaviours, avoid addictions of any kind and
            have faith in religion. Apart from these, he also started teaching four noble
            truths to people. They are:

                The world is full of suffering.

                Suffering  is  the  result  of  people’s  greed  and  attachment  to  materialistic
                world.

                Everyone can get rid of the suffering through salvation.
                Salvation can be achieved by following eight fold paths. They are: right

                thought,  right  speech,  right  action,  right  effort,  right  memory,  right
                understanding, right livelihood and right meditations.

            The place where the Buddhists pray and study is called the Vihar or Gumba.
            Tripitaka and Jatak are the major religious books of the Buddhists. The main
            festivals of the Buddhist are Baishakh Purnima and Lhosar. Vihars and Gumbas

            are  main  religious  place  where
            Buddhists go to pray.

            Kirant religion

            Kirant  is  also one  of  the  oldest
            religions followed in our country.
            The Kirantis worship the nature like
            trees, mountains, jungle, river, etc.                 Udhauli Parva



                                                                 SOCIAL STUDIES - GRADE 8    53]]></page><page Index="54"><![CDATA[The religious place of the Kirantis is known as Margathan. Phalgunanda Lingden

            is the Guru of this religion. The main festivals of the Kirantis are Ubhauli and
            Udhauli Parva. The religious book of the Kirantis is called Mundhum. Paruhang
            and Sumnima are the two deities worshipped by the Kirantis.

            Christianity

            Jesus  Christ is the founder of

            this religion. Christians believe
            that Jesus  is the son of god sent
            as the  savior of humanity. Bible
            is the main religious book of the
            Christians.  The  place  where  they

            pray the lord Jesus Christ is known
            as  the  church.  Christmas  is  main
            festival observed by the Christians                      Church

            on the 25  of December. It is the birth day of Jesus Christ. The main teachings
                      th
            of this religion are to forgive others, adopt good behavior, help the needy, and
            take care of the disabled and the poor people. The essence of this religion is
            love, compassion, generosity and humanity.

            Islam religion

            Muslims are the followers of Islam
            religion. They follow the teaching

            of Hajarat  (Prophet)  Mohammad.
            His teachings are concerned about
            the ways of getting rid of worries
            in our lives. Donating to the

            needy, adopting good habits, being
            truthful,  helping  the  poor and                        Masjid
            protecting the religion is the main teaching of this religion. The Muslims pray
            to Allah also known as Khuda and their religious book is called Quran.

            The place where people worship their lord is called Masjid. The major festivals

            observed by them are Id, Bakra Id, Ramjan, Id-Ul-Fitr, etc.


            54  SOCIAL STUDIES - GRADE 8]]></page><page Index="55"><![CDATA[Shikhism

            The  Sikhs follow  the  teachings  of

            Guru Nanak. Their religious book is
            known as Guru Grantha Sahib. They
            do not believe in worshipping idols.
            The place where they pray to their
            god is known as Gurudwara. Sikh

            teaching  emphasizes  the principle
            of equality  among  all  humans,  and
            rejects discrimination on the basis of

            caste, creed and gender. They should
            follow the guru’s teachings, help the
            poor, avoid violence, be friendly and                    Gurudwara
            polite with everyone and protect their religion. The hymns of the Gurus are
            known as Gurbani.


            There are other religions which are followed around the world like Jain, Bahai,
            Sinto, Tao, etc.



















             Key Terms
            Addictions  : complete dependence on something
            Deities     : gods and goddesses
            Emphasize  : give special importance to something
            Hymns       : a religious song
            Sympathetic : understanding and concerned

            Note to the teacher: Show some pictures about the popular religions of Nepal and start a discussion about
            those different religions.

                                                                 SOCIAL STUDIES - GRADE 8    55]]></page><page Index="56"><![CDATA[Evaluation Exercises



            Activities

            1.  Meet people belonging to different religion in your community and discuss
                with them about their religion.

            2.  Find out the different ways to worship  the god by people belonging  to
                different religions.


            Very short answer questions

            1.  What do you mean by religion?
            2.  Define religious tolerance.

            3.  What is Secularism?
            4.  When was Nepal declared as secular state?

            5.  What is the holy book of Islam religion?
            6.  When is Christmas celebrated?

            7.  What is Gurudwara?
            8.  Who is the teacher of Kirant religion?

            Short answer questions

            1.  Fill the table below with the similarities and differences of these religions:
                    Similarities                           Differences
                 Teachings          Hindu    Buddha Kirant Christian Muslim             Sikh

                 Religious books




            2.  Write down the ideology of your religion.

            3.  What is meant by Sanatan religion? Mention the important teachings of
                Hinduism.
            4.  What are the eight fold paths of Buddhism?

            5.  List out the teachings of Buddhism.
            6.  Who are the followers of Kirant religion? What do they worship?

            7.  Nepal is declared a secular state. Write its importance.

            56  SOCIAL STUDIES - GRADE 8]]></page><page Index="57"><![CDATA[Lesson

                3                        SOCIAL HARMONY




            Nepal is geographically, culturally and socially diversed country. We can see
            diversity in the people living in different parts of this country. The climatic

            condition of the country is very different in the Mountain region, Hilly region
            and Terai region. People living in these parts of the country have their own
            costumes, language, religion, lifestyle and culture. It is very difficult to find any

            Rural Municipality or Municipality where people of only one caste or religion
            live. The most beautiful feature of our country is unity in diversity.

            All  the  three  regions  are  interdependent  on  one  another. The  rivers  flowing
            from the Mountains reach the Terai that facilitate in the process of irrigation.

            This in turn helps in the agricultural production. The crops grown in the Terai
            region is transported and consumed by the people of the Mountain and Hilly
            region. The electricity  produced in the Hilly region is supplied to the Terai
            region. It helps to run the factories and industries of Terai region. So all parts

            of the country are dependent on each other and support each other for survival.
            Many people from Mountain and Hilly region go to Terai in search for work and
            education. We can find many professionals like teachers, social workers, and
            health workers, etc from Terai who are working in Mountain and Hilly region.

            The people from every region get support, love and respect from each other
            regardless of their origin. Even though Nepal is a multi-lingual, multi-religious
            and multi-cultural country, there isn’t any difference and conflict between the
            religions, castes and cultures. We believe in social harmony.


            We  respect  each  other  and  live  in  harmony. This  is the  true  spirit  of social
            harmony that is embodied into each Nepalese’s mind. We have to create our
            own individuality and try to contribute as much as possible in the developmental
            work of our country. Our caste, religion, language can be different but united

            effort can push us to development.

            Note to the teacher: Make the students enact role play or understand the events relating to social harmony
            in their community and encourage them to maintain harmony amongst themselves.

                                                                 SOCIAL STUDIES - GRADE 8    57]]></page><page Index="58"><![CDATA[Key Terms
            Consume        : buy goods and services
            Embody         : give a visible form to an idea, feelings or characteristics
            Interdependent : dependent on each other
            Irrigation     : to supply water on lands with the means of pipes
            Survival       : to live or to exist



                              Evaluation Exercises


            Activities


            1.  List the things  that you and your family need to do to maintain  social
                harmony.
            2.  Present any effort made in your community for maintaining social harmony
                in the class.


            Very short answer questions
            1.  What is social harmony?

            2.  How do you maintain good relation with your friend? Write in a sentence.

            Short answer questions
            1.  List out the ideas that help in maintaining social harmony in the community.
            2.  How do you protect your own traditional identity and deal with people
                belonging to another traditional identity?

            3.  How are the different regions interdependent on each other?
            4.  Is there social harmony in your society? Why?

            Community Work


            Go around your community and visit at least 20 houses and fill the table given
            below. Then prepare a report on ‘Social harmony in my community’.

                Home            Cast/         Mother                      Disabled people
                Owner        Surname          Tongue        Religion           yes/no







            58  SOCIAL STUDIES - GRADE 8]]></page><page Index="59"><![CDATA[Lesson

                4           NEPAL: A BEAUTIFUL GARDEN




































            Nepal  is a culturally  rich  country.  There  are  various costumes,  folk songs,

            music,  dance,  art  and  culture  that  belong  to  the  people  of  different  regions.
            People  from  Mountain  region  to Terai  region  are  not  only  different  in  their

            conducts but are also different in their physical and facial structure. They also
            speak different languages and follow different culture. They celebrate different

            festivals  like  Dashain,  Tihar,  Chhath,  Buddha  Jayanti,  Udhauli,  Ubhauli,
            Maghe Sankranti, etc.


            Nepal  is  similar  to  garden  where  different  types  of  flowers  bloom.  The
            fragrance  of  these  flowers  enchants  the  whole  garden  making  it  beautiful

            and pleasant. In a similar manner the diversity of Nepalese people makes it a
            beautiful country where each community has something unique to give back

            to the nation. This essence of Nepal makes its people feel proud and happy.




                                                                 SOCIAL STUDIES - GRADE 8    59]]></page><page Index="60"><![CDATA[Late King Prithvi Narayan Shah lovingly once said, “Nepal Char Jaat Chhattis

            Barna Ko Sajha Phulbari Ho”.


            According to the census of 2068 BS, there are 123 languages spoken in
            Nepal. Most of these languages have a written script. These languages are our

            identity  and  they  are  all  our  national  languages.  Nepali  has  been  chosen  as
            the common language as not everyone understands all the languages. This is

            the official language of Nepal as well. There are 125 castes and 10 religions
            followed in Nepal.  According to the census of 2068 BS, Hindu 80.62%,

            Buddhist 10.74%, Muslim 4.20%, Kirant 3.60%, Christian 0.45%, other groups
            0.4%.


            The National Anthem of Nepal  “Sayau Thunga Phulka Haami Eutai Mala
            Nepali” refers to the people of Nepal who are similar to hundreds of flowers

            knitted into one large garland.

            Nepali is also the medium  language  to other dialect  groups.  The major

            languages of Nepal according to 2011 AD census are Nepali 44.6%, Maithali
            11.7%, Bhojpuri 6.0%, Tharu 5.8%, Tamang 5.1%, Nepal bhasa 3.2%, Magar

            3.0%, Bajjika 3%, Doteli 3.0%, Urdu 2.6%. The regional languages Awadhi,
            Bhojpuri, Maithali, etc are spoken in the Southern Terai region.












             Key Terms

            Conduct  : behavior and manner
            Consume  : buy goods and services
            Essence  : fundamental nature
            Fragrance  : scent
            Unique    : only one of its kinds

            Note to the teacher: Exhibit clothes, paintings, song and dance reflecting unity in diversity.
            60  SOCIAL STUDIES - GRADE 8]]></page><page Index="61"><![CDATA[Evaluation Exercises



            Activities

            1.  Look at the picture given below and write down a song or poem or draw a
                picture to put down your feelings that the below picture has generated.





















            2.  Nepal is a country of diversity. Discuss in the class on this topic.


            Very short answer questions

            1.  What do you understand by unity in diversity?
            2.  How many languages are listed and how many languages are spoken in
                Nepal?

            Short answer questions

            1.  There is Unity in diversity Nepal. Explain.
            2.  ‘Nepal is a beautiful garden.’ Present your logics.

            3.  ‘Nepal  is  a  multi-lingual,  multi-ethnic,  multi-cultural  and  multi-religious
                country.’ Justify.
            4.  How has our national anthem helped to promote unity in diversity?


            Community Work

            Go around your community and observe various costumes, cultures or festivals
            then draw a picture reflecting such things and display in the class.







                                                                 SOCIAL STUDIES - GRADE 8    61]]></page><page Index="62"><![CDATA[Lesson

                5                    NATIONAL HERITAGE




            Heritage  means  anything  that
            is inherited  or handed down to
            the people from generation  to
            generation. The things that  do not
            belong to a person, community
            or group but belong to the nation
            are  known as National  Heritage.
            It can be anything of national
            significance which is handed down
            and preserved through generation.                   Patan Durbar Square
            Every individual of the country has
            equal rights towards that heritage. Each country has its own National Heritage.
            The  examples  of National  Heritages  are  religious places,  temples,  forests,
            Mountains, rivers, etc. Similarly, our costumes, folk music, festivals, traditions,
            songs, music,  dance,  Jatras,  archaeological  sites, and  historical  places  and
            objects are also our National Heritage.

                 Participation of people in the “Bagmati River Clean-Up Campaign”

            Women  Environment  Preservation  Committee  (WEPCO), Lalitpur  Sub-
            Metropolitan  City  and  Kathmandu  Engineering  College  under  mutual
            cooperation organized the “Bagmati River Clean-Up Campaign”. 50 members
            from  different  organization  took  part  in  the  campaign.  The  members  from
            organization  like  WEPCO, Lalitpur  Sub-Metropolitan  City, Kathmandu
            Engineering  College,  Pokhareli  Didi  Bahini  Samuha,  Friend’s Club,  JICA
            etc actively  participated  in campaign  to clean  the polluted  Bagmati  River.
            The clean-up spot was Bagmati Bridge at Kupondole. The clean up materials
            and tools were provided by Lalitpur  while volunteers and members were
            coordinated by WEPCO. The tricycles from WEPCO were used for collection
            of the waste after the clean up. The Metropolitan trucks were used to transport
            the waste. The total amount of waste collected in first week was 2 Trucks with
            capacity of 4 tons. While, Total amount of waste collected on second week was
            3 Trucks with capacity of 4 tons.


            62  SOCIAL STUDIES - GRADE 8]]></page><page Index="63"><![CDATA[Most countries have  passed laws to protect National  Heritage  Sites.
            The UNESCO publishes a list of National Heritage Sites that are unique and
            represent  the culture  of the country.  Those are considered  internationally
            important. This list contains heritages from all over the world. It is a matter of
            pride for any country to be on this list. UNESCO has included the following
            properties of Nepal on the World Heritage lists:


            1.  Kathmandu Valley (Cultural Heritage)
            The Kathmandu  Valley  World Heritage  property includes  seven Monument
            Zones. They are:
            i)  Kathmandu Durbar square

            ii)  Patan Durbar square
            iii)  Bhaktapur Durbar square

            iv)  Swayambhunath Stupa
            v)  Bauddhanath Stupa
            vi)  Pashupatinath Temple

            vii) Changu Narayan Temple
                                                           Bhaktapur Durbar Square
            2.  Lumbini (Cultural Heritage)
            3.  Chitwan National Park (Natural Heritage)
            4.  Sagarmatha National Park (Natural Heritage)

            National Heritages are identity of our country. They reflect our past civilization,
            culture and tradition. So, they need to be protected for the future generation.
            Following measures should be taken to preserve our National Heritages.
                 Creating public awareness among the people about the importance  of
                National Heritages,

                 Periodical renovation and maintenance of our heritage sites,
                 Formulation of strict laws and its effective implementation,
                 Management of security system around the heritage sites.


             Key Terms
            Campaign          : work in an organized and active way towards a goal
            Civilization      : the society, culture, and way of life of a particular area
            Naming Convention : a meeting for the purpose of naming things
            Note to the teacher: Make the students participate in project works relating to the preservation of National
            Heritage Site. Also take them for an educational tour around a local heritage site.

                                                                 SOCIAL STUDIES - GRADE 8    63]]></page><page Index="64"><![CDATA[Evaluation Exercises



            Activity

            List the ancient and important National Heritage found in and around your
            community.


            Very short answer questions
            1.  What is National Heritage?
            2.  What are the properties of Nepal that are enlisted in World Heritage Sites?
            3.  What does national heritage reflect?

            4.  Why should we preserve heritages?
            5.  Write the full form of UNESCO.
            6.  How does the national heritage enhance our pride?
            7.  Which organization is responsible for preparing the list of World Heritage
                Sites?

            Short answer questions
            1.  What is National Heritage? Write its importance.

            2.  Write a travel journal including your experience of travelling to any one
                World Heritage Site.

            3.  Our heritages are being damaged day by day. List the ideas to protect these
                heritages.
            4.  Write about one such heritage site in your community which has not been
                included in the World Heritage Site.
            5.  Write an application to the Rural Municipality/Municipality requesting to
                include the National Heritage found around your community in the World
                Heritage Site.
            6.  If you are given an opportunity to enlist any National Heritage Site of Nepal
                in World Heritage Site, which one site will you enlist and why?

            Community Work

            Visit a historical, religious or tourist sites in your community. Then prepare a
            report including all the points given below:
            a) Background of the visit                    b) Objective
            c) Method                                     d) Findings
            e) Conclusions                                f) Suggestions

            64  SOCIAL STUDIES - GRADE 8]]></page><page Index="65"><![CDATA[Lesson                       INTERNATIONAL

                6                            PERSONALITY




            Florence Nightingale

            We have often visited hospitals and seen nurses
            taking care of the sick people. The nurses work

            very hard looking after the patients.  Their
            responsibility  is  to  provide  medicine,  give  care
            and assistance to the sick people. In the earlier
            years, this profession was carried out by men and
            it wasn’t considered to be a respected job. In these

            circumstances Florence Nightingale took up this
            profession. She showed to the world that women
            could equally take care of the sick people and help        Florence Nightingale

            them recover. Her step was a big example for the           (1820 AD - 1910 AD)
            people all around.

            Florence was born on 20  May, 1820 AD in Italy. Her parents wanted her to get
                                      th
            married to a rich gentleman and settle down but she refused. She had different

            plans for herself. She wanted to take care of the sick people and help them. She
            was a very caring girl from her childhood. She used to take care of her dolls
            as if they were real people. She even helped the sick and needy people in her
            village. At the age of 17, she

            decided to take up nursing            Florence Nightingale at Scutari
            as her profession. She felt
            that it was her calling.
            She went  to Kaiserswerth,

            Germany to be trained
            in  the  field  of  nursing.
            During the Crimean war in
            1854  AD, she along with         A scene from “A Pageant of Nursing” to be presented by Dundee nurse in the Gaumont

            her team of 38 nurses went       on Sunday–Florence Nightingale with the wounded at Scutari. The pageant is in aid of
                                                        the Royal College of Nursing education appeal.

                                                                 SOCIAL STUDIES - GRADE 8    65]]></page><page Index="66"><![CDATA[to take care of the injured soldiers in the army hospital of Britain. The condition

            of the hospital was pathetic. It had poor hygiene and sanitation. Due to the
            lack of proper care, a lot of people were dying. She with her fellow workers
            cleaned the hospital. Florence didn’t even rest at night. She walked from one

            patient’s bed to the other with a lamp on her hand making sure that everyone
            was alright. The soldiers lovingly called her the ‘Lady with the Lamp’ or ‘Lady
            Bird’ and this is how she is recognized even today. She used to write letters on
            behalf of the soldiers letting their families know that they were fine. She was a
            true friend to them. Her efforts were recognized once she came back from the

            Crimean war. She was awarded with the order of merit in 1907 AD for her hard
            work and dedication. She established a hospital named Scutari. She dedicated
            all her life to the sick people and she passed away on 13  August 1910 AD.
                                                                          th
            Every year 12  May is observed as International Nurse Day to commemorate
                           th
            her birth and the roles of nurse.

            Mahatma Gandhi

            Peace is one of the most important necessities
            in the world. Peace is an occurrence of harmony
            characterized  by  lack  of  violence,  conflict
            behaviors and the freedom from fear of violence.


            Mohandas Karamchand Gandhi was  born on
            2  Oct 1869 AD. He is the epitome of peace and
              nd
            non-violence.  He  never  believed  that  violence
            could give us  any solution for our problem.

            He proved and showed to the world that
            tolerance,  patience  and  peace  can  lead  us to         Mahatma Gandhi
            better  solutions.  During  the  freedom  fight  in       (1869 AD - 1948 AD)

            India, he guided millions of people into the path of non-violence. One of his
            famous saying is ‘In a gentle way, you can shake the world’. His efforts paid off
            and India got its freedom from the British rule.

            He launched non- violent  movements like non-cooperation  movement,

            quit India movement  and civil  disobedience  movement.  He stopped the
            non-cooperation movement when the protestors became violent. They burnt the
            66  SOCIAL STUDIES - GRADE 8]]></page><page Index="67"><![CDATA[police station where several

            policemen  were killed.
            Even though his colleagues
            urged him to make the

            movement  violent,  he still
            stood  by  his  principles.
            His determination  won
            over others and they had
            to follow the  path  he led.

            He believed in the theory
            of ‘simple living, high thinking’. He used to sleep on the floor with a single
            bed sheet spread on it. He wore simple clothes and always promoted the

            domestic products. He also started ‘Charkha Movement’ with the intention of
            promoting Indian made clothes. He believed that a country could be developed
            and move forward only if we encourage  our domestic  products. Mahatma
            Gandhi is not only recognized  in India but he has been a great  example  of
            non-violence for people all over the world. Mahatma Gandhi led the Indians

            to challenge the British-imposed tax on salt with 240 miles long walk from
            Sabarmati to Dandi. It is called Dandi Salt March. On 12  March 1930 AD,
                                                                          th
            Gandhi made his own salt and denounced the salt tax. Gandhi also launched

            the Quit Indian Movement in 1942 AD for the British to quit India. He was
            imprisoned for many years in both India and South Africa. Finally, India got
            independence on 15  August 1947 AD. Gandhi, a great person was assassinated
                                 th
            at the Birla House (now Gandhi Smriti) by Nathuram Godse on 30  January
                                                                                    th
            1948 AD at the age of 78 in New Delhi, India.




             Key Terms

            Calling    : a strong urge towards a particular way of life or career
            Colleagues : a person with whom one works in a profession or business
            Epitome    : a person or thing that is a perfect example of a particular quality or type
            Launch     : start something
            Pathetic   : weak and useless

            Note to the teacher: Bring a famous personality’s biography and share the summary of it in class.

                                                                 SOCIAL STUDIES - GRADE 8    67]]></page><page Index="68"><![CDATA[Evaluation Exercises


            Activities

            1.  ‘Simple living, high thinking.’ Prepare a speech on this topic. Invite a social
                worker of your community and conduct the program yourselves.
            2.  Find quotes on peace said by different international personalities. Write
                them down on a chart paper and display them on different areas of your
                school. Some of such quotes are given below:
                a)  Where women are honoured, there the god rejoices. (Manu)
                b)  For to be free is not merely to cast off one’s chains, but to live in a way
                    that respects and enhances the freedom of others. (Nelson Mandela)
                c)  Those who deny  freedom to others deserve  it not for  themselves.
                    (Abraham Lincoln)
                d)  Better than a thousand hollow words, is one word that brings peace.
                    (Buddha)
                e)  We could never learn to be brave and patient, if there were only joy in
                    the world. (Helen Keller)

            Very short answer questions
            1.  Who are called International Personality?
            2.  When and where was Florence Nightingale born?
            3.  Why is Nightingale called ‘the lady with the lamp’?
            4.  What was the award given to Nightingale and why?
            5.  What was the real name of Mahatma Gandhi?
            6.  When and where was Gandhi born?
            7.  When did India get independence from British rule?
            8.  Why did Gandhi start ‘Charkha Movement’?
            9.  What is Dandi Salt March?
            10. When and where did Gandhi pass away?

            Short answer questions
            1.  Write a letter to your friend explaining what you have learnt from the life
                of Florence Nightingale and Mahatma Gandhi.
            2.  What role did Nightingale play at Scutari hospital in Turkey?
            3.  How did Nightingale improve the condition of the soldiers of Crimean War?
            4.  Why did Gandhi withdraw Non Co-operation Movement?
            5.  ‘Simple living, high thinking.’ Justify this statement relating with the life of
                Mahatma Gandhi?

            Community Work

            Ask your parents about a person of your community who has served other
            people or is a social worker and prepare a report.
            68  SOCIAL STUDIES - GRADE 8]]></page><page Index="69"><![CDATA[Review Exercise



            Give short answers:
            1.  Why is Badghar considered to be important in the Tharu Community?
            2.  What are  the benefits enjoyed by  the  Guthiyars through  Guthis in  the
                newar community?

            3.  What would happen in the Gurung community if there was no Rodhighar?
            4.  How does Bheja unite the community?
            5.  Write an Introduction of the Dhikuti in the Thakali community.

            Project Work

            Find out if your community practices the custom of parma or not? If yes, find
            out about its condition in the present time. Prepare a report by asking the chief

            person of 10 families based on the following questions:
            Questions to be asked to the chief member of the family:
            a)  Do you know about the custom of parma and paicho?
            b)  Do you take interest on small amount of money that has been lent or borrowed?

            c)  What are the benefits of parma and paicho?
            d)  What needs to be done to preserve such customs?


            Example of a report of project work.

                       The custom of parma and paicho in my community
                I belong to the rural community of Nepal. We conducted a survey on 27  Bhadra, to
                                                                                   th
                know the condition of the parma and paicho customs in my community. We collected
                data from 10 houses in the neighbourhood. The following are the findings of the survey:
                70% of the family in my community are aware of the parma or paicho custom. The
                custom of parma was quite popular in the past few years. But people these days prefer
                to work on daily wages that is the reason why the custom of parma is becoming extinct.
                The custom of paicho and parma helps in strengthening the bond between the members
                of the community. To maintain this custom a few points need to be considered as below:
            a)  Returning honestly the things that you have borrowed (paicho) on time.
            b)  The condition of the thing should be as it was in the time of borrowing.
            c)  When you borrow the labour of somebody, make sure that you pay the parma on time.
            d)  When you go to help others then be honest regarding your work and work as if you are
                being paid on daily wages.
                If these customs are maintained then it would help the community by giving them the
                feeling of unity.


                                                                 SOCIAL STUDIES - GRADE 8    69]]></page></pages></Search>